<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two presentments of the grand jury in Bristol at the general quarter-sessions of the peace, holden there in October, 1681.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Court of Quarter Sessions of the Peace (Bristol). Grand Jury.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3529</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29039</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10798045</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10798045</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45956</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45956)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1391:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two presentments of the grand jury in Bristol at the general quarter-sessions of the peace, holden there in October, 1681.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Court of Quarter Sessions of the Peace (Bristol). Grand Jury.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Second presentment has caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Court of Quarter Sessions of the Peace (Bristol). --  Grand Jury.</term>
               <term>Trials --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45956:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO PRESENTMENTS OF THE GRAND JURY IN BRISTOL, AT THE General Quarter-Seſſions OF THE PEACE Holden there in <hi>October,</hi> 1681.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXXXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:45956:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45956:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div type="presentment">
               <head>To the Right Worſhipful, <hi>Thomas Earle,</hi> Eſq MAJOR; and to the Worſhipful Court of Aldermen, His Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace for this Ctiy of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and County of the ſame City, now Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in the General Quarter-Seſſions of the Peace, begun the 4th day of <hi>October,</hi> in the three and thirtieth year of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Reign, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1681. and by Adjournments continued to this preſent 19th. day of the ſame.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>The Humble Preſentment of the Grand Inqueſt.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WE, the <hi>Grand Jurors</hi> for the Body of this City, and County of the ſame City, being by the Sacred Obligation of an Oath. Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to us at our firſt entrance into this Service and Truſt, and alſo by that Suitable and moſt Excellent Charge given Us purſuant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, Engaged to Enquire for Our Soveraign Lord the King, for the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the ſaid County, in Diſcharge of the ſaid Obligation do Preſent as followeth.</p>
               <p>The Excellency and Neceſſity of Laws and Government are more then inſinuated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Us by the Early Proviſion made for them, even in the Infancy of the World, and firſt Original of things; and alſo by the ſpecial Care and Conſtant Endeavours that have been ever ſince uſed for keeping the ſame Sacred and Inviolable, and for delivering of it ſo, down to Poſterity through all Generations unto theſe days.</p>
               <p>The unſpeakable Miſeries, Miſchiefs and Dangers which inevitably follow on the want hereof, we need not have recourſe to former times to relate; the Preſent Age having felt effectually the ſmart thereof, and many of our ſelves cannot but remember.</p>
               <p>On the other hand, the great Benefit, Satisfaction, and Comfort, which are reſtored when the Government is returned to its Antient Conſtitution, as it was by the miraculous Reſtoration of his Sacred Majeſty to his Throne and Dignity; and the Bleſſed Effects thereof which we have enjoyed for above twenty years laſt paſt; cannot be of leſs weight than to perſwade all (whom their own Wills and Intereſts have not hardned into Obſtinacy) to the Higheſt and beſt Eſteem of our preſent Governments, and to exert their utmoſt endeavour towards the Countenance and Support thereof.</p>
               <p>It is heartily to be wiſhed that all men would be of ſuch Good Principles, and Ingenuous Diſpoſitions as to live contentedly and Obediently under the beſt Government, of the beſt of Princes; and in the enjoyment of the beſt of Priviledges, the Proteſtant Religion, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Property and Peace can afford us. But Experience teaches us that thô it may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, yet it can never be expected; whilſt Intereſt leads men the contrary way, whilſt Diſobedience is ſo interwoven with ſome mens Creeds, and whilſt Rebellion doth paſs for a Profitable Sin.</p>
               <p>This Year hath been a Year wherein the face of Publick Affairs have appeared in great variety; it hath been a year of Great Expectation, of Great Diſcoveries, Great Endeavours, and Great Diſappointments. Providence hath ſeemed to be involved in a Cloud, and to diſcover it ſelf only by its Chequer Workings; notwithſtanding all which being now Happily arrived at the End thereof, and having this Opportunity put into our hands, we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45956:3"/>cannot but with all Humility and Thankfulneſs of Heart, acknowledge the Infinite Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Mercy of Almighty God exerciſed towards us in the manifold mercies we ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy; in the Gracious Continuation of Health in our Dwellings and Peace within our bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; when moſt part of our Neighbour Nations are imbroiled in Wars, and the diſmal conſequences thereof. For preſerving the Kings Majeſty in his happy Reign over us, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the wicked Machinations of the ſons of Violence, whereby they have Diligently ſought to Murder, or Depoſe him; and thoſe, whether our Open and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Enemies, of the Religion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or other Seditious and Ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men, who under pretence of Zeal, Religion, and Loyalty, put themſelves in a Better Condition to perpetrate their Wicked Deſigns; who thô from Differing Intereſts, and unto Differing Ends, yet concur with the former in this Third thing; The Ruin of Monarchy, and the Subverſion of the Government. But the hand of Juſtice hath Begun to find them out, and hath Diſtrbuted to ſome of them the Juſt Reward of their Treaſonable and Wicked Enterprizes. So that there is Good Hopes that Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance will not ſuffer ſuch Murderers to eſcape, and that ſuch Blood-thirſty and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful men ſhall not live out half their Days.</p>
               <p>Alſo we return our True and Unfeigned Thanks to our Soveraign Lord the King for all thoſe Unſpeakable Benefits which from the Throne of his Majeſty are Freely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed for the Advantage of his People, for his great Wiſdom in Foreſeeing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Dangers, and taking timely care to Prevent them from falling on his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. And for all thoſe frequent inſtances of his Grace and Goodneſs towards this City; and more eſpecially for his Gracious Condeſcention in his laſt moſt Gracious Declaration, to give the meaneſt of his Subjects an account of ſome of the Greateſt of his Actions, wherein amongſt many other things (of his Royal Bounty promiſed) he is pleaſed to inſert his Special Care of the Proteſtant Religion as by Law eſtabliſhed; his Intentions of Governing by Frequent Parliaments, and his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions that he will never ſuffer his People to be Ruin'd by Arbitrary Power, either of Himſelf or their Fellow-Subjects.</p>
               <p>In the next place we Preſent our Hearty Thanks to the Worſhipful Sir <hi>Richard Hart,</hi> late Mayor of this City, for the Several and Singular inſtances of his Extraordinary Readineſs and Care in Serving this City in thoſe Emergent Occaſions which happened in the year of his Majoralty; In the beginning whereof things appeared with a Sad and Diſmal Aſpect, for that the Factious Party in this City being grown to a Head, knew no Bounds to their own Miſchievous Deſigns: Firſt they Branded the Magiſtrates and Miniſters, and other his Majeſties beſt Subjects with the Odious Name of Papiſts; then they procured ſeveral Aldermen to be Seized on and Impriſoned. The the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> late Sheriffs to be taken into Cuſtody, our Miniſters, to be ſeveral of them ſeverely Threatned and one (with whom they began) to be ſeverely Handled, to be under a long Confinement, and expoſed to their Malitious Slanders by Libellers and Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leteers even of their own Procuring, and all this at great Diſtance from their Own Homes, to the vaſt Expence of their Eſtates and manifeſt Hazard of their Lives. For Accomplifhing whereof, they got themſelves admitted Members of ſuch Clubs in <hi>London,</hi> as made them fitter for Acting this, and what they had farther Projected. And then they proceeded publickly to Threaten utter Ruin to ſeveral other Aldermen; many Members of Common-Council, and other ſubſtantial Inhabitants of this City to the number of ſeveral Scores at once, under the Notion of Pulling down the Artillery; and no leſs then utter Undoing to a whole <hi>Grand Jury</hi> for Declaring their Opinion in the matter of Petitioning.</p>
               <p>They go on (by their Old refuge of Lyes) to render the Intereſt of this City very Contemptible in the Face of the Nation, openly Declaring at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> before the Members of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, that our Mayor was there a Factor for the Abhorrers of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and that Himſelf was one of them, and did publickly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare before the Commons of <hi>England</hi> that it was a Crime in <hi>Briſtol</hi> in the year 1679 to Acknowledge that there was any Popiſh Plot. All things ſeeming to lye at the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45956:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>of their falſe Tongues, and to be Obnoxious to the Proſecution of their unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Anger.</p>
               <p>It was now Crime enough to be declared Loyal, and almoſt Capital to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>radi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <hi>F<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticiſm,</hi> for to that Confidence were they grown, That theſe Words [<hi>You ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer this before the Houſe of Commons</hi>] were as confidently ſpoken by the moſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable of them to thoſe that were not of their Judgment on very Trivial Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions as a Man in Authority may ſay to a Thief [<hi>You ſhall be ſent to Priſon</hi>] or to a Drunkard [<hi>You ſhall be ſet by the Heels.</hi>] Thus intending to carry all before them; to what further Heights they would have proceeded, neither themſelves nor any other could know, had not Deliverance ariſen in ſuch a way as they never thought of, except it was to to damn it as Impoſſible.</p>
               <p>This was the time wherein our ſaid then Mr. Mayor was pleas'd to (the manifeſt hazard of Himſelf, his Credit and Eſtate,) to interpoſe and aſſert the Right and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of this City, and with great Care and Induſtry did bring off the Cauſe thereof very much to its Reputation and Advantage; for which, and for his Readineſs to do the like on all other Occaſions, and for the whole Management of Publick Affairs du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his year of Mayoralty, we preſent him with our Hearty Thanks.</p>
               <p>We likewiſe preſent our Hearty Thanks to the Worſhipful Court of Aldermen for their readineſs to Stand by, and Encourage, and Aſſiſt our ſaid May or in all thoſe things that tended to the Publick Good: For that by your Joynt Endeavours herein the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and Reputation of this City is publickly retrieved, ſo that his Sacred Majeſty hath been graciouſly pleaſed to conceive Better and more Friendly thoughts of us, and we hope for the future will find no cauſe to eſteem us otherwiſe than as one of his Loyal Cities.</p>
               <p>The little Experience which we have had within the ſpace of one year laſt paſt hath let the World ſee, That when men of ill Principles ſet their Ambitious eyes upon the Government. Their reſtleſs Endeavours will ſtick at nothing which they think may conduce to the bringing it into their Hands; and that thoſe who think themſelves too good to be Governed by Law, think all others but good enough to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Law from them. But Bleſſed be God we now ſee the Creſt of the Faction fairly fallen, the Countenance of its Abetters Dejected, and their Actions receive publick Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement ſo that the great Expectation they had of fingering once more the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Government, being wholly for this time Diſappointed: We do hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh they would now ſit down contentedly under the Government as it is already Eſtabliſhed, as it becomes Good Chriſtians and Dutiful Subjects: but if not, if they will ſtill perſiſt to trouble the Waters for their own more profitable Fiſhing—We all know the Law is made for the Lawleſs and Diſobedient, and the Sword of Juſtice is intruſted in the hands of the Miniſters of Juſtice for the Chaſtiſing of evil Manners, and for the puniſhment of evil Doers, as well as for the encouragement of them that do well: and therefore if the Laws Enacted are in force, and if Laws in force were intended for the Good of the People, by whom, and for whom they were made; we hope and expect that we ſhall never have cauſe to complain of our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates for denying to us the Benefit of thoſe Laws in not applying them to the ends of our Advantage, for which they were at firſt ſo deſigned, and afterwards committed to their Adminiſtration.</p>
               <p>We ſhould not have ſaid ſo much on this particular had it been the Condition of this Place alone: but the true <hi>Vox Patriae,</hi> in all the Loyal Addreſſes lately preſented to the Kings Majeſty, agree that the cauſe of all the troubles we have been ſenſible of, or may now fear, hath been occaſioned by thoſe amongſt us, who by Diſſenting from, declare themſelves Enemies to the Government as it is now Eſtabliſhed, and that the only way to preſerve Peace is to bring the Actions of all men to be conformable to thoſe wholſom
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45956:4"/>Laws, by which all good men endeavour to regulate their Lives; and againſt the Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities and Execution whereof, none but the Guilty and Self-condemned Criminals Storm and Revile.</p>
               <p>We do therefore Recommend it to your Worſhips, as a matter moſt worthy your utmoſt care, The Obſervation and Preſervation of the good Laws of this Kingdom, in Reference both to Eccleſiaſtical and Civil Concernments; That you by all means Diſcourage all manner of Prophaneſs and Debauchery; That you continue to be Conſtant and Vigorous Aſſerters of the Proteſtant Religion according to the Laws of this Kingdom now eſtabliſhed, the true Profeſſion whereof is an Antidote againſt the numerous evils we lye under, and the Cauſes of what we farther fear; and a Thorough United Conformity whereunto would be an Invincible Bulwark againſt the wicked Machinations of all our Enemies: And that you would be pleaſed always to endeavour the Preſervation of the Peace of this City by all thoſe means the Law hath preſcribed, and Experience hath taught are neceſſary to be uſed.</p>
               <p>Many things have been preſented to this Court, and now lye before your Worſhips by former <hi>Grand-Juries;</hi> particularly thoſe of <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Midſomer</hi>-Seſſions laſt, which we Recommend to your Worſhips care, as worthy to be conſidered of in order to their Amendment: Many things alſo have been Preſented by the Conſtables of the ſeveral Wards in this Quarter-Seſſions: And what other things have further come to our Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, we have Ennumerated in a Paper hereunto annexed; To which we humbly refer the Court; and conclude with Our Hearty Prayers that God would Bleſs all your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Endeavours for the rendring of this City an United and a Flouriſhing City: That God will bleſs this Kingdom with the great Bleſſings of Proſperity and Peace, and all his Majeſties Subjects with the Bleſſed Effects thereof. And chiefly, that God would bleſs the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty with Health, Length of Days, Victory, Riches and Honour: That he may live to ſee the Fruit of all his extraordinary Care, and Wonderful Wiſdom, in Swaying the Scepter of theſe Kingdoms, returned to him in Love and Loyalty from all his Subjects. That thoſe that Riſe up againſt Him may be as the Duſt before the Wind: That all his Enemies may be cloathed with Perpetual Confuſion, and that upon his Sacred Head and the Head of his Royal Poſterity, the Crown may for ever Flouriſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="presentment">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45956:4"/>
               <head>ANOTHER PRESENTMENT OF THE Same Grand-Jury AT ANOTHER ADJOURNMENT OF THE COURT, <hi>Viz.</hi> The Twenty fourth day of <hi>October,</hi> 1681. <hi>To the Right Worſhipful,</hi> Thomas Earle, <hi>Eſq Mayor of this City,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>The Humble Preſemment of the Grand Inqueſt.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WE, The <hi>Grand Jurors</hi> for the Body of this City and County, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—Having drawn up our former Preſentment, with intention to have given it into the Court on a former Adjournment; ſince which time ſome New Matter being come to our Knowledge, which we cannot without apparent Violation of our Truſt, neglect to bring before your Worſhips, do make bold farther to Preſent.</p>
               <p>And we do therefore Preſent, That the Court of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> and General Goal-delivery held for this City and County, being Lawfully called upon the eighteenth day of this inſtant, <hi>October;</hi> The Wilful Departure of Sir <hi>Robert Atkins,</hi> our Recorder, from the ſaid Court, and thereby annihilating the ſame (his Preſence being eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to the Conſtitution thereof,) after the <hi>Grand Jury</hi> were Sworn, the Juſtices on the Bench, the appearance of Proſecutors and Witneſſes in ſeveral Notorious Murders
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45956:5"/>and Felonies attending, and the Bills of Indictment againſt ſome of them, (<hi>viz.</hi> One againſt <hi>Nicholas Butler</hi> for Felony and Burglary, another againſt <hi>Francis Warden</hi> for Felony and Burglary, and another againſt <hi>Elizabeth Windgett,</hi> for Murdering her Baſtard Child, being by the ſaid <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> found, and ready to be delivered into Court: The She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs ready attending with their Goal, and the Priſoners at the Bar waiting their Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, is a moſt Unpreſidented denyal of Juſtice, and a moſt Unwarrantable and Arbitrary Proceeding. In compariſon whereof, the ſo much complained of Diſcharge of a <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> in <hi>Middleſex,</hi> ſome time ſince, before their uſual time of being Diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (there being only a poſſibility the Bills might be preferred to them: And the Court continued ſtill to be a Court, and to do Juſtice without them) is not ſo much as to be mentioned or thought of: This neceſſarily tending to the Impunity of Notorious Offenders, beſides other Miſchiefs; as the Proſecutors and Witneſſes being Diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of their Recognizances, by the Diſcontinuance of the Court; The Offenders conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in Gaol without Proſecution; His Majeſties Gracious Charter to this City, by which the ſaid Court is Granted, beyond expreſſion, Affronted; The Mayor and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, his Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace, openly Contemned; The Honour and Juſtice of this City greatly Diſparaged; and his own Unfaithful Execution of his Office, as Notoriouſly Betrayed and made Publick.</p>
               <p>And it is our Opinion that his endeavouring to avoid the Swearing of Sir <hi>Richard Hart,</hi> an Alderman, is not only an Aggravation of this Offence, but another denyal of diſcharging his Duty: For he, the ſaid Sir <hi>Richard Hart,</hi> being by the ſaid Sir <hi>Robert Atkins</hi> himſelf, together with the Mayor and Court of Aldermen, <hi>Nemine Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente,</hi> Legally and Duly Elected, the Swearing of him became a Duty Executive i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Mayor and Recorder, the Arbitrary part of it being determined by the Election: For ſhould it be in the Power of the Mayor, or Recorder, or both, to refuſe Swearing as Alderman duly Elected, the very Conſtitution of Aldermen, on which the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of this City doth principally depend, as it is preſcribed in our Charter, would neceſſarily be Deſtroyed; and the whole Power of making Aldermen be virtually devolved into the Mayor and Recorder alone.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we make it our humble Requeſt, that either by Complaint to the Kings moſt Sacred Majeſty, or by Diſplacing the ſaid Sir <hi>Robert Atins,</hi> or by ſuch other Methods of Proceedings, as to your Worſhips ſhall ſeem moſt Fitting and Effectual, we may be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed for this preſent Grievance, and be ſecured for the Future againſt ſuch Failure of Juſtice, and Arbitrary Proceedings within this City.</p>
               <closer>God Save the King.</closer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>James Millerd.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Holliſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nicholas Standfaſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Joſeph Bullock.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Samuel Rogers.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Jaſper Caus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Francis Fiſher.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Scarborow Chapman.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Mathew.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Jones.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Davidg.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Francis Ballard.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Bachellor.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Eſtwick.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John England.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
